A Guide to the Paul B. Barringer Papers 1913-1919
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Paul B. Barringer Papers 1913-1919
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
RG 2/6
3 boxes and 1 oversized folder (2.4 cubic feet)
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open to research.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Board of Visitors elected Barringer as the sixth president of Virginia Polytechnic Institute on 17 May 1907. Accomplishments of his administration included: entrance requirements raised from four to fourteen units; a Farmer's Winter Course established; summer school expanded. Barringer's tenure as president was not a smooth one, hampered by several investigations. From the start, he was determined to develop the agricultural facet of the College until it was at least equal to the engineering component, which caused some dissatisfaction among certain alumni and faculty. In 1909, the Chairman of the Alumni Association Welfare Committee, Lawrence Priddy, attempted to have the Board of Visitors oust Barringer. The Board ordered an investigation and a public hearing was held 25 March 1910, at which Priddy's charges were dismissed as "unwarranted" and "inaccurate." However, this was not the end of Barringer's problems. In the fall of 1911, the Board again called for an investigation when a former Commandant of Cadets accused Barringer of "countenancing immorality" on campus. The investigation concluded that the charges were "without foundation." Having survived those investigations, Barringer next ran afoul of Governor Mann, who wanted the College to become involved in agriculture extension work. Barringer did not agree, so Mann said he would appoint a Board of Visitors antagonistic to Barringer if he did not resign. On 10 June 1912, Barringer resigned, but the Board asked him to remain in office another year until a new president was selected.
Scope and Content Information
This collection contains mainly incoming and outgoing correspondence (1907-13) concerning college activities and issues of Barringer's administration including: academic standards; hazing; Hog Cholera outbreak (1908); fires; prohibition; water/sewage system; refrigeration plant; advantages and dangers of football. A few letters from Barringer are to United States presidents: Theodore Roosevelt; William Howard Taft; Woodrow Wilson. Also included with the collection are the following items: ledger of Board of Visitors Executive Committee minutes, handwritten (24 September 1904 - 1 November 1904 and 2 October 1906 - 12 June 1908); inventories (1908-11); letters of application for faculty positions (1909); several items relating to charges against Barringer by Lawrence Priddy, president of Alumni Association, and ensuing investigation (1910); correspondence and other items concerning Mess Hall investigation (1911); purchase orders (1911); reports to the Board of Visitors (1911); leases and contracts; report by Barringer to Board of Visitors on professors, giving names, ages, teaching hours per week, salary, degrees, and Barringer's personal remarks on each (no date).
Arrangement
This collection is arranged according to subject matter.
Contents List
- Paul B. Barringer
  - Correspondence 1906-1914
    - A-Miscellaneous 1908-1910 (Box-folder 1-1)
      - Correspondence with Edwin A. Alderman, president, University of Virginia (UVA)
      - Notable letterhead: Artesian Mfg. and Bottling Co.
      - Correspondence with Virginia Anthracite Coal and Railway Company, including rate on coal Merrimac to Blacksburg; establishment of telegraph service from Merrimac to Blacksburg
      - Correspondence from Virginia Railway Company regarding fares from Merrimac to Norfolk ($2.00 roundtrip) for the Thanksgiving Day football game
      - Letter to W. E. Addison, Lynchburg News (2-11-11) regarding Afro-American terminology
      - Correspondence from Arnold Totman, University Club, Chicago regarding refusal to place Virginia Polytechnic Institute on list of accredited institutions
    - B-Miscellaneous 1908-1910 (Box-folder 1-2)
      - Correspondence with Joseph Bryan regarding Davis Bill and UVA's preparation for extension of agricultural department to meet profits of the bill. 1/11/1908
      - Otto Burkhart's appointment as professor of Mining Engineering
      - Notable letterhead: International Textbook Company, International Corrrespondence Schools (Scranton PA)
      - Correspondence from F. Donaldson Brown regarding possible moving of Geological Survey Bureau from Virginia Polytechnic Institute to the University of Virginia
      - Notable letterhead: Baldwin Detectives letter regarding charges for Negro detective for whiskey cases
      - Correspondence regarding hazing incidents
      - Cannon on lawn of Barringer's former residence
      - Correspondence regarding individual students
      - Notable letterhead: Blacksburg Power and Supply Co.
      - Correspondence regarding crusade against tuberculosis at Virginia Polytechnic Institute
      - Testing and treatment of cattle
      - Correspondence to J. M. Barker requesting collection of light tobacco for exhibition
      - Letter from W. M. Brodie, assistant to the commandant, regarding why the Military Department asked that the religious service be held in the dining hall instead of in the chapel
    - B-Miscellaneous 1910-1911 (Box-folder 1-3)
      - Correspondence regarding price of manure
      - Correspondence from Julian A. Burruss regarding problems with administration of Virginia Polytechnic Institute (VPI)
      - Notable letterhead: Brown-Forman Co., Kentucky Whiskies
      - Southern Educational Association, H. E. Bierly, secretary
      - Notable letterhead: Great District Fair
      - Correspondence from W. K. Brainerd, Dairy Husbandman, regarding tuberculosis condition in the dairy herd
    - C-Miscellaneous 1908-1910 (Box-folder 1-4)
      - Hazing incidents
      - Correspondence to Corporation commission of Virginia regarding local rates for coal
      - Correspondence regarding Farmers Winter Course at VPI
      - Letter from members of the Senior Class regarding foreign language requirement
      - Notable letterhead: Cyphers Incubator Company
      - Death of J. W. Churchman
      - Notable letterhead: Medical College of Virginia
      - Letter from Barringer to the Board of Trustees, Carnegie Endowment for International Peace regarding practicability of eliminating military tactics and training from the curriculum 5/15/1911
      - Dairy herd records
    - C-Miscellaneous 1912-1913 (Box-folder 1-5)
      - Correspondence regarding T. N. Conrad Memorial
      - Country school fairs
      - Correspondence from J. de la Cova, Compania de los Puertos de Cuba letterhead 12/28/1902
      - Notable letterhead: Craddock-Terry Company
      - Notable letterhead: Hotel Patten
      - Notable letterhead: Clark Bros. and Co., Dealers in Leaf Tobacco
      - Letter from Lyman Carrier with recommendations for the Department of Agronomy
      - Correspondence regarding salary for assistant to the librarian, Miss Ethel A. Lacy
      - Correspondence with S. B. Chumbley regarding Black property
      - Letter to the raven Society with donation for memorial over the grave of Elizabeth Arnold Poe
      - Conference for Education in the South
      - Letter to Town Sergeant, Chas. W. Camper regarding Negroes in town selling whiskey to students 2/6/12
      - Correspondence regarding no extensions of leave to students except for family sickness
    - D-Miscellaneous 1908-1911 (Box-folder 1-6)
      - Correspondence regarding various House and Senate bills, including Davis Bill
      - School of Mines
      - Correspondence regarding safety of football
      - Correspondence from Commandant Dashiell regarding quality of Mess Hall food
      - G. H. Denny, Washington and Lee University
    - D-Miscellaneous 1912 (Box-folder 1-7)
      - Coal supply
      - A.W. Drinkard
      - Entrance requirements
      - Notable letterhead: Dick's Hotel Agency
      - Letter to Donald Derickson indicating problems with Civil Engineering school
      - Notable letterhead: Monticello Hotel
    - E-Miscellaneous 1907-1909 (Box-folder 1-8)
      - Notable letterhead: J. D. Eggleston, Superintendent of Public Instruction, Commonwealth of Virginia Davis Bill
      - Teachers of the agricultural and mechanic arts
      - Proposal for inauguration of high schools for teaching of agricultural and manual training
      - Hazing crisis and dismissal of students involved
      - Establishment of experiment station at the State Farm
      - Proposed organization of a Graduate Department
      - Proposed summer school for high school teachers of agriculture
      - Bill appointing a committee to look into management of the state institutions
      - Mill Tax bill
      - Idea of placing VPI under same Board of Visitors as UVA (Barringer's letter to Eggleston, Superintendent of Public Instruction of June 4, 1908) June 4, 1908
      - Farmers' Winter Courses
      - Property of Lebanon College
      - Bureau of lectures
      - Charges against the administration at VPI
    - E-Miscellaneous 1910-1912 (Box-folder 1-9)
      - Correspondence with J. D. Eggleston, Superintendent of Public Instruction
      - United Agricultural Board Bill
      - Economy Shoe Repairing Co.
      - Charges against Barringer
      - Correspondence from S. W. Fletcher, director, Virginia Agricultural Experiment Station regarding funding, budget, and salaries
      - Correspondence with F. W. Eheart, mayor, Blacksburg, regarding Sunday pumping charges
      - Correspondence with B. Ellison, steward regarding Mess Hall fare
    - F-Miscellaneous 1908-1911 (Box-folder 1-10)
      - Improvement of the wagon road between the coal bins and the power house
      - W. O. Frith, Attorney-at-Law
      - J. G. Ferneyhough, State Veterinarian
      - Bonfire nuisance
      - Notable letterhead: Virginia Fair Circuit
    - F-Miscellaneous 1912-1913 (Box-folder 1-11)
      - Letter to D. F. Freeman with treasurer's report on the value of state property at VPI
      - Letter to Hon. H. D. Floor, House of Representatives from W. Brainerd regarding relations to the dairy stock of the state
      - Water supply
      - Movable Schools
    - Fletcher, S. W. 1907-1911 (Box-folder 1-12)
      - Pamphlet, "Twelve Stereopticon Talks Upon Agriculture and Gardening"
      - Report concerning the Virginia Agricultural Experiment Station
      - Installment of private branch telephone exchange upon the campus
      - Department of Bacteriology and Mycology
      - N and W Railway Farmers' Institutes
      - School fair work
      - Need for Department of Extension teaching
      - Proposed seed law
      - Agricultural High Schools
      - Crop Pest situation
      - Land for the Experiment Station
      - Attendance at Movable Schools of Agriculture
      - Telegraph service
    - Ferguson, Meade 1908-1909 (Box-folder 1-13)
      - Solitude House
      - Faculty housing
    - Fletcher, Meade, Director of Experiment Station 1912-1913 (Box-folder 1-14)
      - Proposed Department of Forestry, Irrigation, and Drainage
      - Needs of the institution
      - Resolutions of the State Farmers' Institute
      - Budget of State Fund
      - Proposed sites for local Experiment Stations
      - Weather observations at Blacksburg
      - Virginia Polytechnic Institute Needs pamphlet
    - G-Miscellaneous 1907-1911 (Box-folder 1-15)
      - Jason H. Gibboney, Norfolk and Western Railway Co.
      - Rison Bill
      - School of Mines bill
      - Shoes stolen from freshman
      - Notorized statements and correspondence regarding signals for plays at George Washington football game
      - General Alumni Association
      - Changes in the uniform
    - H-Miscellaneous 1908-1911 (Box-folder 1-16)
      - Notable letterhead: Yellow Sulphur Springs, letter from J. H. Holt
      - Students' Contingent fee
      - Notable letterhead: Roanoke Transfer and Cab Co.
      - Report of the VPI Infirmary
      - Improvement of heating system
      - Notable letterhead: from Evans, Almirall and Co. Engineers and Contractors
      - Report on heating systems for VPI from Evans, Almirall and Co.
      - Letter to Senator Jno. M. Hart (Jan. 20, 1912) regarding needs of Virginia Polytechnic Institute Jan. 20, 1912
      - Letter from Barringer to President D. H. Hill (May 6, 1911) regarding movement to remove the words "and including military tactics" from prescribed instructions May 6, 1911
    - H. D. Holt 1908-1909 (Box-folder 1-17)
    - I-Miscellaneous 1910-1912 (Box-folder 1-18)
      - William D. Ingles
      - Draper's Meadow Massacre site
    - J-Miscellaneous 1907-1913 (Box-folder 1-19)
      - Exhibit at Jamestown Exhibition
      - Trespassing stock
      - "Better Farming Special" on the railway
      - Tuberculosis in Holstein cattle
      - Letter of April 24, 1909 to members of congress regarding appropriations to George Washington University April 24, 1909
      - Letter to Captain G. H. Jamerson regarding morals of the Corps Sept. 16, 1911
      - Letter from Barringer to Hon. Chas. A. Johnston regarding desire to buy Edward Black farm and state legislature's funding of VPI. relative to other state schools Feb. 26, 1912
    - K-Miscellaneous 1908-1911 (Box-folder 1-20)
      - Notable letterhead: Monopol Tobacco Works
      - Notable letterhead: A. Black Company, Inc.
      - Correspondence from G. W. Koiner, commissioner, Department of Agriculture and Immigration, Commonwealth of Virginia regarding why they should not be moved to the Library Annex
      - Rate slip for Virginia Polytechnic Institute from Virginia Department Office, South-Eastern Underwriters Association
    - L-Miscellaneous 1908-1913 (Box-folder 1-21)
      - Sugar beet experiments
      - Local roads
    - M-Miscellaneous 1907-1909 (Box-folder 1-22)
      - Student matters
      - John M. McBryde
      - Faculty resolution regarding the death of W. S. Martin
      - Correspondence regarding refrigerating line, sewer lines
      - Tuberculosis situation in cattle
    - M-Miscellaneous 1910 (Box-folder 1-23)
      - N. S. Mayo, Animal Husbandry
      - Inventory, Animal Husbandry Department
      - Tuberculous in cattle in the Department of Animal Husbandry
      - D. O. Matthews
      - Freight charges and handling
      - William Hodges Mann, governor, Commonwealth of Virginia
      - Winter course (one month) of instruction for practical farmers
      - Report of Dean of Engineering
    - M-Miscellaneous 1911 (Box-folder 1-24)
      - William Hodges Mann, governor, Commonwealth of Virginia
      - United Agricultural Board for extension work at Virginia Polytechnic Institute
      - Improvements in the facility for fire protection
      - Carlton McCarthy, State Accountant
    - M-Miscellaneous 1912 (Box-folder 1-25)
      - W. Hodges Mann, governor, Commonwealth of Virginia Tech United Agricultural Board
      - Movable schools
      - Animal husbandry
      - Tuberculin tests of cows
      - Expression of interest in VPI by family of a Persian student
    - N-O-Miscellaneous 1908-1912 (Box-folder 1-26)
      - Miss L. A. Neilson, Executive Clerk and Registar at VPI
      - Letter to Governor Oddie of Nevada regarding establishment of Rural Constabulary "by reason of the presence of the Negro in the South"
    - P-Miscellaneous 1907-1908 (Box-folder 1-27)
      - Jamestown Exhibition materials
      - Shops Department, Virginia Polytechnic Institute
      - Water system from Painter Spring
      - Advisability of building a hotel in Blacksburg
      - Notable letterhead: F. J. Kress Box Co.
      - Age of entrance is 16
      - Expense receipt
      - Contingent fee
      - Notable letterhead: Prairie State Incubator, Co.
    - P-Miscellaneous 1909-1913 (Box-folder 1-28)
      - Connection of Virginia Anthracite Coal and Railway Co with the Virginian Railway
      - Price of coal
      - J. R. Parrot, Professor of Mechanical Arts and Director of Shops
    - R-Miscellaneous 1907-1909 (Box-folder 1-29)
      - Rhodes Scholarship Proximity of privy to water supply
    - R-Miscellaneous 1910-1913 (Box-folder 1-30)
      - Proximity of privy to water supply
      - Notable letterhead from the Hotel Richmond
      - Professor L. S. Randolph's report on the proposed contract with Appalachian Power
    - S-Miscellaneous 1907-1908 (Box-folder 1-31)
      - Mechanical Arts
      - J. H. Slusser and Sons, Brush Mountain Coal
      - Student affairs
    - S-Miscellaneous 1909-1913 (Box-folder 1-32)
      - Notable letterhead: Eastern Viavi Co.
      - Cold Storage propositions
      - Faculty housing
      - Dairy farm, creamery, and College barn--permission to ship cream into Washington, D. C. revoked
      - Cattle sold by the institute, tuberculosis among cattle
      - Graduates who enjoy exceptional salaries [Barringer's letter of July 15, 1910] July 15, 1910
      - Notable letterhead from the Peninsular and Occidental Steamship Company
      - Montgomery County Medical Society
    - T, U, V-Miscellaneous 1908 (Box-folder 1-33)
      - Notable letterhead: Decatur Chamber of Commerce
      - Creamery and cattle matters
      - State farm for utilitarian versus research uses
      - Barringer's letter to Dr. E. L. Trudeau regarding his attempt to cure tuberculosis in cattle [March 9, 1908] March 9, 1908
      - Freight rates for coal
    - T, U, V-Miscellaneous 1909-1912 (Box-folder 1-34)
      - Scarlet fever situation
      - Bee keeping (Italian colonies)
      - Newspaper attacks on Experiment Station
      - Changes in the uniform
    - W-Miscellaneous 1906-1913 (Box-folder 1-35)
      - College Estimates 1906-07
      - College Estimates 1908-09
      - Equipment expenses 1907
      - Notable letterhead: Springfield Fire and Marine Insurance Company
      - Barringer's letter to Dr. William H Welch regarding his research [March 6, 1908] and Trudeau method March 6, 1908
      - Correspondence from Wilson and Foreman, Attorneys & Counsellors at Law regarding claim against the dairy business as conducted by VPI
      - Correspondence regarding Barringer's relationship to the literary societies
      - Dr. F. D. Wilson
      - Financial matters--institute out of debt
      - Bonfire nuisance
      - Intoxicants on campus
      - Letter to Dr. Walter F. Wilcox regarding racial relations April 8, 1911
      - Charles I. Wade, Secretary and treasurer, V. P. I.
      - Charge No. 9 against Barringer
      - Col. J. F. Ware, Commandant
      - Notable letterhead: Enterprise Foundry and Machine Works
    - Charles I. Wade, Secretary and Treasaurer, VPI 1910-1914 (Box-folder 1-36)
      - Auditor's report 1910-1911
    - X, Y, Z-Miscellaneous 1909-1913 (Box-folder 1-37)
      - Emma S. Yerby, principal, Blacksburg High School
  - Administrative Files 1904-1913
    - Prospective Students 1908-1909 (Box-folder 1-38)
    - Account Vouchers #38218-38277 1908 (Box-folder 1-39)
    - Account Vouchers #60593-60632 1912 (Box-folder 1-40)
    - Account Vouchers #60593-60632 1912 (Box-folder 1-41)
    - Academic Evolution and Land Grant Politics 1908-1912 (Box-folder 1-42)
      - Notable letterhead: Barker-Jennings Hardware, Co.
    - Advertisements, 1909-1910 (Box-folder 1-43)
    - Agricultural Experiment Station 1907-1912 (Box-folder 1-44)
    - Establishment of Agricultural High Schools 1909 (Box-folder 1-45)
    - Alumni 1907-1909 (Box-folder 1-46)
    - Alumni Gateway 1909-1913 (Box-folder 1-47)
    - Animal Problems 1915-1919 (Box-folder 1-48)
    - Athletic Association 1911-1912 (Box-folder 1-49)
    - Applications for Positions 1913 (Box-folder 1-50)
    - Barringer-Biographical, Genealogical, Personal 1907-1912 (Box-folder 1-51)
    - Barringer-McBryde Transition 1906-1907 (Box-folder 1-52)
    - . "Better Farming Train," 1908-1909 (Box-folder 1-53)
    - . Blanket Letters, Student Lists 1908-1910 (Box-folder 1-54)
      - Farmers' Winter Course
    - Board of Visitors 1904-1909 (Box-folder 1-55)
      - Dining Hall
      - English Department
      - Road improvements
    - Board of Visitors 1908-1912 (Box-folder 1-56)
    - Burruss' Bid for Presidency 1908 (Box-folder 1-57)
    - Carnegie Foundation 1908 (Box-folder 1-58)
    - Cholera (Hog) Outbreak 1908 (Box-folder 1-59)
      - Notable letterhead: Walter M. Carroll, Breeder of Thoroughbred Stock and Poultry
    - Cholera (Hog) Outbreak 1908 (Box-folder 1-60)
      - J. G. Ferneyhough, State Veterinarian
    - Corps of Cadets 1906-1911 (Box-folder 1-61)
    - William R. Dashiell, Commandant 1909 (Box-folder 1-62)
    - Department Reports 1911-1913 (Box-folder 1-63)
    - Discipline, etc. 1910-1912 (Box-folder 1-64)
    - Discipline, etc. 1910-1912 (Box-folder 1-65)
- Paul B. Barringer
  - Administrative Files 1906-1913
    - Education Commission of Virginia Tech 1906-1912 (Box-folder 2-66)
    - Executive Council Minutes, [bound book] 1904-1908 (Box-folder 2-67)
    - Faculty 1908-1911 (Box-folder 2-68)
    - Faculty 1912 (Box-folder 2-68a)
    - Faculty-Committees, etc. 1909-1911 (Box-folder 2-69)
    - Fires [Creamery] 1909 (Box-folder 2-70)
    - Fraternities 1911-1913 (Box-folder 2-71)
    - Geological Survey, State 1908 (Box-folder 2-72)
      - Proposed Rison Bill
    - Hazing 1908-1910 (Box-folder 2-73)
      - Letter to J. M. Morris, president, Corps of Cadets regarding raid made by students on Negro settlement and damage to the property of Granville Smith.
    - Inaugural Parade 1909 (Box-folder 2-74)
    - Ingles, Mary 1912 (Box-folder 2-75)
    - Inventories-Reports, Needs of Dept., Professors 1908-1910 (Box-folder 2-76)
    - Inventories-Reports, Needs of Dept., Professors 1908-1910 (Box-folder 2-77)
    - Inventories-Reports, Needs of Dept., Professors 1908-1910 (Box-folder 2-78)
    - Investigation-Barringer 1909-1910 (Box-folder 2-79)
    - Investigation by Welfare Committee 1910 (Box-folder 2-80)
    - Investigation-Charges Preferred 1910 (Box-folder 2-81)
    - Investigation-Richmond Times Report 1910 (Box-folder 2-82)
    - Investigations-Court Report by Archer Johnson 1910 (Box-folder 2-83)
    - Investigations-Court Report by Archer Johnson 1910 (Box-folder 2-84)
    - Library 1909-1910 (Box-folder 2-85)
    - Local 1909-1913 (Box-folder 2-86)
    - Mess Hall 1909-1912 (Box-folder 2-87)
    - Mess Hall Investigation (see also Investigations)--Applications for Dining Hall Steward 1911-1912 (Box-folder 2-88)
    - Mess Hall Investigation 1911-1912 (Box-folder 2-89)
    - Movable Schools 1909-1911 (Box-folder 2-90)
    - North Carolina College of Agriculture and Mechanic Arts-Athletic Relations 1909 (Box-folder 2-91)
    - Parrott, J. R. 1908 (Box-folder 2-92)
    - Policy 1908 (Box-folder 2-93)
    - Publications, Student 1908 (Box-folder 2-94)
    - Purchase Orders 1909-1910 (Box-folder 2-95)
    - Priddy, Lawrence 1908-1910 (Box-folder 2-96)
      - Correspondence regarding Andrew Carnegie.
    - Prohibition 1909 (Box-folder 2-97)
    - Quick Matters 1907-1909 (Box-folder 2-98)
      - Notable letterhead: Bluefield Inn
      - Notable letterhead: Murphy's Hotel
      - Notable letterhead: Ebbott House Army and Navy
      - Notable letterhead: Interstate fair Association, Lynchburg, Virginia
    - Refrigeration Plant 1906-1910 (Box-folder 2-99)
      - Notable letterhead: H. W. Johns-Manville Co.
    - Refrigeration Plant 1906-1910 (Box-folder 2-100)
    - Railroad 1909 (Box-folder 2-101)
    - Roosevelt, President Theodore 1908 (Box-folder 2-102)
    - Scott Case 1908 (Box-folder 2-103)
    - Smithfield 1906-1911 (Box-folder 2-104)
      - Report of the operations of the college Farm and Smithfield farm for the fiscal year 1905-1906
      - Sewage, washwater, and polution of the stream that flows through Smithfield